[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net se radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software welcome to software engineering
radio my guest today is Francis bontempo
she has been programming professionally
since the 1990s in fields such as
Banking and quantitative Finance
she's the editor of accu's overload
magazine and has a PHD in Data Mining
and machine learning her new book which
we'll be discussing today is learn C++
by example she previously published a
book titled genetic algorithms and
machine learning for
programmers welcome to the show Francis
thank you in this episode we're going to
discuss the C++ programming language
most people think of C++ as an
object-oriented language but it's
perhaps more accurately called a multi-
paradigm language what paradigms does
C++ enable or support loads and loads of
things I mean I guess historically C++
started as what was referred to as C
with classes so a lot of people do think
of C++ being as
objectoriented and you can use it like
that but a lot of people nowadays
particularly with some things like
ranges and some of the new features
taken board a more functional approach
to things so that gives you a whole
different perspective and then of course
at some point during the history of C++
Evolution we introduced templates and
somebody observed that you could do a
surprising amount of things at compile
time with templates you end up with
crazy template metaprogramming things
which are possibly a bit Niche can be
useful sometimes and they're just kind
of plain fun but you can do o you can do
straight up procedural stuff and end up
with things that look like C instead you
can do a much more functional approach
which I personally quite like C++ is a
compiled language and its execution
speed is one of its trademarks what are
some of the pros and cons of being a
compiled language though the compiler
can find mistakes for you if you use the
type system well but that's something
you need to learn to do it means that
you're compiling two specific specific
Hardware so various optimizations can
kick in that can give you the speed if
you've written your code well I mean you
can write bad slow code in any language
but because you're compiling to a
specific Target you don't have levels of
indirection going on so that speeds
things up so execution speed and you've
already mentioned sort of the type
system and touched on generic
programming I think those are all
strength that you hear a lot about what
would you say some of the the weaknesses
might be of C++ or maybe I should say
like the challenges of using it in a
production environment or learning it
the usual quote at this point is from
Spiderman with great power comes great
responsibility so you are in control and
that means that you can do all kinds of
silly things you can get things wrong
lots of people at the moment are talking
about safety there's a big discussion
going on around that and I guess some
languages like rust are trying to
challenge C++ because you can overrun
bounds if you're not careful if you rely
on things like the vector type and
various other parts of the language you
can avoid a lot of the problems with
overrunning bounds and dereferencing
invalid memory addresses and so on but
you can completely mess things up really
easily some of my early programming was
in using embedded devices one of which
was a barcode scanner and I overrun a
buffer and it left the laser switched on
which was nearly ended up pointing
straight at my face so yes you can break
all kinds of things because you've got
the power and you can see what's going
on I guess an analogy might be like if
you're driving a car if you got a manual
car or a stick however you word that
you've got more control over what you're
doing versus sitting in a self-driving
car that does what it thinks and yeah
you can break things but you can do
things better as well you've just got
more power and more Choice part of the
safety question with C++ is that it's a
superet of C so you can kind of program
in C style without using say smart
pointers or standard array is that
something that comes up when people are
learning to program that you have to
guide them towards these C++
features I guess it depends where people
are coming from to start with I've seen
so many training materials out there
that do go straight into pointers and
allocating manually with new and then
having to remember to do delete because
I think a lot of of people our sort of
age have come to this from maybe a c
back ground and have learned the new
things as they've cropped up but there
just one or two people who managed to go
look let's just use the sensible safer
things find out about the danger later
on if you really need to I think if
somebody wants to pick up C++ now if you
find a book or some teaching materials
that have got chapters and chapters on
pointers and pointer
arithmetic probably don't read that
first find something that tells you
about vectors and standard array and
doesn't have the word new or delete
anywhere in sight stick to the safe
sensible things yes and I think your
book definitely takes that path of
trying to teach the more modern features
yeah one sort of developer experience
thing I don't think was discussed in the
book is a package manager so many
languages I've used today you have a
centralized package system and you can
sort of just type the name of any
dependency and it gets kind of included
C++ to my knowledge doesn't have a
package manager what's the correct it
doesn't have a package manager there are
several rival package managers out there
there there's some Microsoft offerings
and I won't be able to list all of them
but there's a v package I think Conan a
lot of people have talked about and I
should probably be able to think about
five or six others but my mind has
blanked at this point there are lots
there's no one standard thing people are
using using another thing I've not gone
into in my book is modules which gives
you another way of packaging things up I
think this is going to evolve I think
we're trying to do that as a community
but we haven't settled on one standard
way of doing things whether we ever do
or not we shall see but there are
package managers out there there just
lots of them and some things are
packaged in one place or another place
so yeah you'll frequently end up just
cloning and building the Li as you need
you mentioned Community what sorts of
communities tend to embrace C++ today if
you're at a C++ conference who are the
people you're likely to run into what
industries are they perhaps from my
background a lot of my work's been in
Investment Banking and finance so you'll
get people working on maaps libraries
there to do the pricing and the workout
values of things and credit risk and
that kind of stuff so definitely things
around Finance because of the maths
under the hood wanting to do that
quickly and then the games industry as
well that could rattle off loads of
games companies who use
C++ and then another big area is
embedded things so TV set toop boxes
mobile phones that kind of thing so yeah
embedded mafy stuff and games are the
main areas how about Open Source
Products are there any well-known
products that are based in C++ that come
to mind there lots of background
libraries which will be used by other
things a lot of the modern C++ has come
from examples coded up in the Boost
Library which has been around forever
but again that's a library level that's
not aimed at one specific area and of
course there's lots of different
approaches to Graphics libraries there's
several open source things out there
open Graphics libraries and skins over
the top of that so you can play around
and draw things yourself another area
which I don't know much about is audio I
know one or two people who working on
some audio tools as well so lots out
there I think a good example of that
Library phenomena is python dominates
machine learning but at least parts of
the libraries you use for that say
tensorflow and pytorch at least parts of
them are in C++ I think yeah because
Python's an interpreted language you can
swap out the interpreter and there's the
whole siphon project which gives you a
different way of building up code and
it's quite easy to interoperate between
Python and C++ there's several different
ways of doing it but that would allow
you to speed up certain parts and like
you said a lot of the machine learning
stuff under the hood is doing some
C++ okay let's start getting into
talking about the standards a little bit
and then we're going to Pivot into sort
of the contents of the book which is
kind of touching on these different C++
features in the language itself and also
in the standard library but to start C++
was created by bjn strip the first
version was released in 1984
but the first standard was not until
1998 what happened after 1998 as far as
standards and kind of where are we today
how often do new standards come out and
how much of the language is changing
from standard to standard there's a lot
to cover there high level like you said
98 we got a standard different
compilers were compliant with different
parts of it so that made life really
quite difficult so around 98 in the
early 2000s a lot of people were still
using separate libraries to do some of
the standard things and it took a long
time for people to get nearer and nearer
to GCC or Visual Studio tending to have
most of the stuff in there there still
lists of well this doesn't do this and
this doesn't do that but it gradually
got better and more standard there was
then a I might get the date wrong I
think 2003 we got kind of update that
had some slight improvements and people
well the compiler implementers and Tool
Builders started taking some of that on
board then it all went really quiet for
a while and we geared up to having
another new
standard which started as
C++ o x cuz we were hoping it might be
like 2008
2009 and then we just slapped an x on
the end because C++ is standardized and
they're standard meetings and people
vote on things and argue with each other
and it can take quite a long while to
come to an agreement but it ended up
being 2011 so C++ 11 was when the next
big change happened and that brought on
board loads of things particularly from
the booost library like smart pointers
and things like this to just make it
easier and safer and better
and at that point everyone was like this
has taken us so long to get round to
let's try and be more agile let's aim
for every three years and maybe the next
release so C++ 14 will just be smaller
changes maybe slight improvements here
and there and we save the big things for
C++ 17 then you get C++ 20 so we are we
were aiming for every 3 years and we
have stuck with them after that long
time coming for C++ 11 how about the
split between the language which we're
going to start talking about in a second
and the standard Library are those sort
of both developed kind of evenly or does
the standards tend to emphasize the
library it's both kind of an equal
measure I you if you go to iso's working
group 21 so
wg21 web page you can see a list of all
the proposals there I don't have some
stats on hand on the breakdown of where
the different areas are but there
mixture of tinkering with uses of
existing keywords maybe introducing
keywords or changing things changing how
the language works and also adding to
the libraries and under the working
group they people focused on specific
things so maybe in C++ 26 we're going to
end up reflection which is something you
can do quite easily in C or Java but you
can't in C++ really and that's one big
new feature that are come in now whether
that's at the language level or a
library level we'll see it's going to
involve some language changes because we
need some new syntax for it so that's an
example of one thing on the horizon so a
mixture of language and
Library yeah I've done some csharp
programming recently and don't use
reflection at all until you kind of need
it and you maybe use it in a small area
yeah I mean you can get out of hand I've
worked on some C libraries that
everything was inside out and done by
reflection and driven by external files
and that can end up being really hard to
follow if you've got a compelling use
case then you've got a compelling use
case and if you use it where it's
sensible it's really powerful but you
can't do that in C++ at the moment watch
this space let's get into some language
features now your book is called learn
C++ by example and you have a lot of
great examples that are I feel like
they're just the right size for a book
in terms of being able to explain it and
understand it but that does not
necessarily work well on a podcast so we
may or may not get into the examples but
let's at least try to give a flavor of
what's what's in the book so talking
about keywords and the core language
features
there's a keyword Auto that I think has
been around a while but it may be still
newish to some people can you say what
Auto is used for and when is a good time
to use it so that was introduced way
back in C++ 11 loads of people went oh
no because everybody seemed to be
putting Auto instead of int or something
why are you doing this and that turned
into an argument like where'd you put
your braces and things is it a good
thing or is it a bad thing but it was
introduced for a reason and good reason
we also had lambdas introduced which are
Anonymous functions which loads of
different programming language is
support and you can't name what type it
actually is because each Lambda is a
different type you could shuel it into a
standard function but then you'll
copying things and that adds overhead so
in that circumstance if you say all Auto
then the compiler knows what type it is
and that makes things more efficient so
there was some maybe slightly Niche edge
cases where it's definitely the right
thing to do how about the other uses
with say templates is your feeling to
use Auto whenever you can or do you draw
the line somewhere and decide it's going
to obfuscate things when you do generics
previously you'd say type name t and
then do your function or class to do
whatever you can now say Auto instead
either is fine and doesn't really make
much difference it does allow you to say
Auto as the return
type if you don't do that you've got to
then start digging into decal types and
similar around expressions and you end
up feeling like you're stabbing yourself
in the eye with pointy braces and it's
much easier to just write Auto at that
point and let the compiler work it out
bonus new C++ feature at that point you
can constrain things with a concept
slightly so you can say type name or
Auto and say something is invocable or
check see if it's an integral type or a
double type or a pointer or and so on so
you can constrain things and get better
clearer error messages if you make a
mistake so don't just use raw type name
or Auto at that point try and embrace
the concepts as well to give yourself a
helping
hand we're going to talk about Concepts
a little bit more but another feature
related to Auto is this trailing return
type so traditionally
C++ had the return type before the name
of the function which is common in a lot
of language but now there's an option to
I think you mentioned to have Auto be
the return type and then have sort of an
arrow and the return type at the end
yeah can you say when would you use that
form and and what's the advantage of
that that was something that was
introduced quite early on putting Auto
at the beginning instead of say int or
double or whatever and then you can do
that Arrow so minus greater than sign
and work out for yourself what's going
to be returned and it might be the
result of adding two things if I add an
INT and a double well I'll get the
double back I'll get the higher
Precision back actually as it stands now
in a lot of circumstances is you could
just put the auto at the front and not
bother with the trailing return type
because you might not need to be that
specific and the compiler might well
work it out for you but that's just an
interim step on the way there so if you
see auto and then the arrow at the
end in some C++ code that might be a
surprise if you've not looked for the
last 10 15 years and that is allowing
you to be precise about what's being
returned based on what input parameters
you get okay jumping to another topic
how about const expression I'm not sure
how you pronounce it but c n s t x PR
how does it differ from just plain const
which I think means the variable is not
going to be changed but const expression
is slightly different yeah so I think a
lot of people say const exp because
that's highly pronounceable that's one
of the downsides of C++ We've Ended up
with loads of unpronouncable things
if I declare a variable const int xal
42 the compiler will give me an error if
I try and change X at any point during
the function fair enough so const is to
just stop me from mutating and changing
things that's useful and that's as old
as the hills what const x does is it can
it might not it can be worked out at
compil time which means
if you wanted to do some complicated
sums or do some trig or something which
maybe takes a while to work out there
might be a few operations going on if
you make it Conex it can work out the
actual value at compile
time so then you've lost some runtime
overhead and I've seen people produce
examples of some code that's worked out
some quite complicated mathematics and
if you look at the assembler that's
generated it's just got buff just got
the number in there without all the
function calls and things so sometimes
the compiler will be able to work things
out for you and then you've just got the
value baked into your executable now if
it can't do that and your const
expression just calls makes a call on to
the open internet or something does the
compiler notice that or what happens in
that case if it's not really yeah or if
you had some user input or something the
compiler go you asked me to try of tried
tough and then if you look at the
assembly you'll see it is doing the
function calls so it's like a request
help me out if you can compiler if you
can't no problems this might be a small
one but what is the uniform
initialization syntax it is where you
use braces instead of parentheses but
what's what's really the
difference right cool so that was a neat
little thing that was introduced that's
meant to mean that you can just put
braces around anything so my example of
int X I can put in x equals
42 I now I can put curly braces instead
around the 42 so what who cares well if
I had a class or a struct as well I can
put curly braces around the parameters
to the Constructor so we can start being
more consistent and people there's lots
of little edge cases where people got in
a knot
when they try to initialize things if I
want to put two numbers in a vector like
a n and a one if I do curved brackets
around it actually there's a Constructor
that takes a value and count whereas if
I put curly braces around a n and a one
it goes all right no no you want to put
these two values n and one into a vector
and it's more intuitive what's happening
there it does mean that tend to
initialize everything with curly
brackets there was another annoying Edge
case that if I put in X curve bracket
curve bracket and a semicolon what I've
done there instead of zero initializing
the value X I've declared a function
because the syntax is the same as a
function declaration but if I put the
curly braces then that
disambiguates so it makes some things
clearer there are some cases where you
can't really use the curly braces and
some surprising edge cases that happen
because C++ with great power comes great
responsibility we've got rid of some
horrible edge cases and introduced some
new ones so you win some you lose some
but you can if you you'll tend to see a
lot of modern code now just using the
curly braces round initial values for
stuff then it does look more consistent
there are still edge cases to watch out
for though that speaks to what we've
talked about before where you can
program in a c style or you can adopt
these features when you see another
codebase or or or working with another
codebase do you have to kind of assess
what era of features it's using and do
you have to be consistent with that or
how does that play out so many code
bases look so different some of them you
can see the history of how old they are
of all the different styles that go on
other places will
enforce certain coding Styles so when
there have been updates we go back and
we change things I'm quite chilled if
things are slightly inconsistent I can
get over it but I know some people
absolutely hate that and they want all
the braces to be the same and everything
look the same in some ways it doesn't
matter but if you're missing some
opportunities to speed things up or
avoid mistakes then try and ER on the
side of making your life easier always
but yeah there's so many different
projects out there and you will see some
are all very you can't tell who's
written which bit because they're
enforcing a way of writing things and
others slightly untidy it depends it
varies okay a couple more language ones
including we'll talk about this idea of
a zeroc cost abstraction and how that's
maintained but here's one I wanted to
ask about there has been a feature for a
long time in C++ called type DEF where
you can give a long type or any type you
can give it a shorter name or different
name and that's particularly been useful
with templates because templates can
have long yeah names but there's a new
one called I don't know how new called
the using statement and I think this is
preferred can you say when you would use
using versus type def or anything about
him essentially there's no need to use
type def any more so some people are in
fact one guy reviewed one of the
chapters in my book was horrified even
mentioned it but it's something that's
familiar if you've come to this from a C
background or prior to C++ 11 nowadays
just say using where you would have said
type def before using got another
Advantage so if I've got a lookup table
so say a standard map or an unordered
map from a specific key to a specific
value
I might have a lookup of first name to
address or surname to address I could
have a using statement for a lookup and
I could say well I've got some key Auto
or type def key but it's always going to
an address as the value so then I've got
a little family of things that in the
code it say look up everywhere and I
know what a look up is but I might be
varying what the key is so it gives me a
family of templates and you couldn't do
that with type F this is a small one but
I I noticed it because I I don't
remember seeing it in another language
you can have an if statement that has an
initialization portion semicolon a
condition when would you use that it
wasn't obvious to me something that
happened I think way back in C++ 98 if
I've got a for Loop that says I runs
from zero up to whatever the scope of
the variable I my index leaked outside
the for loop on some compilers which
could cause all kinds of confusion you
kind of wanted it to be within those
braces just in the scope of the for Loop
so the if statement you can now do
something similar with so sometimes you
kind of want to set something in if so
you could set it before the if and then
check the value afterwards but then
you've put it in a wider scope if you
put inside the if statement it's just
accessible from inside that if block a
lot of times in C++ if you keep the
scope really small and close then you're
less likely to accidentally change
things or make mistakes but small and
neats often better and in other
languages too just having smaller things
to look at so it just constrains the
scope of a variable to inside the if
tiny little thing but you can avoid
mistakes that way quite easily you
mentioned Lambda already one notable
thing about c++'s Lambda is it doesn't
include the keyword Lambda or or really
any keyword at all it seems to me like
it's square brackets with the parameters
to the Lambda in the square
brackets and also it had some features I
haven't seen before is terms of
capturing you can capture even a
variable by variable basis can you say
if that gets used in practice so
lambda's the main stay of some
functional programming approaches and if
you look at other functional programming
we start talking about closures and then
you end up in the world of mathematics
and all kinds of things about monads but
whatever let's if we keep it focused
here so yes we've got square brackets
first then we've got round brackets as
you'd have with a normal function
declaration so it might take it an INT
or string or no parameters so it might
be empty curved braces or some input
parameters and then curly braces and the
body of the anonymous function or Lambda
and layer but inside that Anonymous
function you might want to use something
from The Wider context so you can close
over that and send in through the square
brackets one of the local variables for
example so then that's captured
in there and enclosed in that packaged
up in that Lambda so that's what the
square brackets are for are the things I
might want to pass by value or by
reference into that enclosed closure if
that it's a phrase are there certain
types of programming where you feel like
lambdas are more useful because I've
seen them a lot in JavaScript because
you have all of these handlers and
callbacks and you're constantly like
registering those does that come up in
C++ that kind of use yeah I mean I guess
you're doing a really similar thing
there and you could package something up
and send it off to threads or whatever
but even it in more straight up use
cases if you've got something that you
want to happen in an algorithm for
example you want to do some kind of
transformation there's the algorithm
header which brings you all the standard
Library stuff and there's a transform
function in there now I could either
send it a instance of a class that's got
a callable member function that does the
work which is defined off somewhere else
and then when you see the calls
transform you go oh now it's making one
of these other classes and then you have
to look somewhere else to see what that
is but if you put a Lambda there
instead that means you can see I'm going
to transform this container using this
function it's all just in one line in
one place to look so it does save you
jumping around just follow following the
code and it's probably more efficient
because we ar making objects over here
as well it makes it neater to read
sometimes if you just got a one liner
that says add two to everything in sight
that's be a tiny little square brackets
round brackets curly brackets X plus two
BOS just neat small Focus again I think
you're saying that a lot of the
algorithms take functions as input and
in those cases it's potentially loads of
them take a un function so will do
something with one thing or maybe a
predicate that tells you something's
true or false and you can build functors
you can build classes but just a one
shot Lambda looks neat I mentioned zeroc
cost abstraction this is kind of a term
that comes up I think when you get into
the the language design or the standard
can you tell us what that phrase means
and maybe how difficult it is for C++ to
maintain that promise of zero cost a lot
of the focus from the standard committee
is trying to ensure that as new features
are added we don't make things slower or
Worse we succeed most of the time but
there's some edge cases that hasn't
quite worked out and there's some
special cases we've built in to try and
ensure that for example things being
returned from a function instead of
being copied over just go straight into
the return value so there are lots of
places where we special case things to
make things more efficient if you're a
ster always uses a phrase pay for what
you use which I think we're talking
about the same thing there just if we're
going to introduce some of these
abstractions and these algorithms
instead of four Loops the code that
comes out is as efficient and actually
sometimes it's more efficient because
the compiler can spot better
optimization opportunities what we're
trying to do is make the code easier for
humans to read but keep the same
efficiency you mentioned returning from
a function I think that's my next
question in terms of move semantics and
perfect forwarding these are things that
I've seen rust people talk about but
most languages don't have these types of
concerns is that something you get into
as an application writer or is it for
libraries when do you have to start
caring about these move semantics you
can probably get away with it without
thinking about it unless you start
writing your own classes in which case
well it's fundamentally is part of a
class or your own type so if you're
doing some basic stuff with some numbers
and things you'll be all right as soon
as you start writing your own class if
you don't result to
polymorphism then you probably don't
need need to think about it was by
default the right thing happen but as
soon as you start
adding some oo style of programming then
you do need to think carefully about or
do I need to be able to copy this does
it make sense to copy this particular
object or not and then we've got the
idea of moving as well which it's an
efficiency if there is no move then
we'll fall back to the copy instead but
yeah you will start needing to think
about what you need to implement at that
point that's always the case it's a very
different view from some other languages
I guess if you look at Java and net
because they use references everywhere
you don't need to move stuff the object
somewhere on the heat that's garbage
collected for you but again C++ great
power great responsibility moves and
perfect forwarding give you the
opportunity to go actually I don't need
to copy everything over and then get rid
of the old one I can just use the old
one so it allows you to rewire things
and find efficient ways of doing things
can get really complicated but you can
keep it simple if you try and design
your classes well and try and do things
by default where possible lots of the
basic building blocks like the smart
pointers do the right thing for you so
if you compose your structures out of
sensible things then you'll make your
life easier and your code would be
quicker one more question on this move
versus copy and then we'll get into
templates more and then maybe back to
some smaller Concepts one manifestation
of this is maybe that Vector has two
methods M Place back and push back can
you say when I would use either of those
so the push back was always there since
98 that will take an object which might
just be something small like an INT or
it might be a bigger class with lots of
stuff going in so it take a whole object
and then it needs to copy that into
space in memory so it's inside the
vector if I do in place back that can
then be moved in
place so that's more efficient in terms
there's less operations you need to do
so that speeds everything up now it's
going to depend on the object itself and
if you've got lots and lots of things in
there and some of them won't move
properly then the Imp Place back is
going to fall back to going can't cope
and have to copy things for you so like
anything else in the language you can
mess things up and though it's supposed
to be more efficient it might be worse
if you've got a horribly big class with
loads in you shouldn't do that and you
should never have done that keep things
small keep things focused and then
things might be more efficient I think
we're saying if you're writing your own
class you might have to provide that
sort of in place back functionality but
you don't necessarily have
to yeah so that's relying on the Move
being there really so yeah these things
are all tied in okay let's move on to
going deeper into templates so a number
of languages have feature called
generics which is very similar but
sometimes you see it limited to things
like I have a list integers versus a
list of floats that's sort of the super
simple example of generics templates get
in C++ get a little more involved but
let's start with one feature class
template argument deduction that
actually looks like it makes things
simpler because it lets you declare a
vector without necessarily saying what
it's a vector of as long as the compiler
can figure it out it looks like it's
using those braces for initialization
there yeah so with the curly braces
again so when we were chatting early we
talked about a vector and I talked about
using uniform initialization syntax to
send in a zero and a one in curly braces
now you and I can see those are both ins
until until we got the type deduction
going on you'd have to spell out STD
colon colon for standard then Vector
then angle bracket in angle bracket and
give it two ins if you look at it you're
like but I've given you two in why I got
to do the angle bracket an in this is
tedious and boring so now you don't need
to say that angle brackets on the type
it can see what you're doing and that's
a good that's a good thing for two
reasons one I'm lazy I don't know about
you that's great Lester read but also if
I were to do n one and
1.2 it would call me out and say now
hang on a minute you've got some ins but
you've got a double in there as well
make your mind up what you want it to be
and it can actually catch some mistakes
there where you are potentially losing
Precision or you're using more Precision
than you need so that's a good thing you
mentioned this one early on but I wanted
to come back to a little bit is deal
type I'm trying to pronounce it y I
think this can be used with templates to
deduce or determine the type of an
expression which is pretty neat when you
see it how does it but I guess when
would you use that I mentioned that near
the beginning of the book just to show
some of how the syntax is changed I
wonder if you're going to ask this and I
was trying to think of a compelling use
case nowadays and to be honest I can't
think of one because I think in most
cases if you just say Auto it will
figure things out for you now someone
listening to this might be able to prove
me wrong and I'm sure they'll let me
know but I think nowadays you can tend
to just say Auto I bet there are some
Niche edge cases I haven't thought of
though to be honest I think I saw it's
used in certain types of templates it
might be related to my next question
which is type traits and and I think you
did touch on this so you have a bunch of
traits like is constructible is
invocable is copy constructible I wonder
if under the hood those are using deal
type yeah if you would start looking at
the implementation of some of those
there will be something going on we used
to have uh idea of only compiling up one
version of a template if it actually
compiled which was a way of overloading
thing which had the stunning name of s
which stood for something like
substitution failure is not an error so
it would just try all the different
variants of templates and see which one
works some of the things around const X
also allow us to do a similar trick with
a bit less syntax you can actually do if
const EXP and compile one way or an else
Branch depending on types of things and
again sometimes you don't then need to
dig into the decal types and the
specifics you can just try adding two
things together and see if it compiles
or not that's something that's been
moving over the last few years and we're
finding newer neater ways of doing
things actually let's jump ahead and
bring up Concepts here so it took me a
while to understand I think why
concepts are important and I think it
does relate to these type traits in the
sense that Concepts let you I guess if
I'm writing a template and the parameter
of my template is a type Concepts let me
prescribe what that type has to support
is that what yeah exactly that so if I
got a list of stuff fine but I might
want say I just want some list of
numeric types because I'm going to or
something that supports addition or
division or something so then I can say
it's numeric and if I try and divide
then this would be fine I don't need to
do that if I just left it as Auto or
type def as soon as I used division or
addition I'd get a compile error I'd
probably get several hundred compile
errors and spend an hour going up and
down trying to work out what the problem
was but if I put the concept at the top
and say right I'm going to use addition
so this type of better have an addition
operator as soon as you declare it the
top compile error will go no concept
failed can't add this up you'll probably
then have the hundreds of other compile
errors as well but at the top it be nah
that's not going to work so that's good
yeah that leads to a question about
compil in general I know some languages
has spent a lot of effort trying to get
their compile erors to be understandable
even I think some of them nowadays you
know you points out where in the line
the ER is coming from how are C++
compile erors these days I did wrestle
with some very long errors having to do
with templates I'm wondering where that
stands today it's much much better than
it was again if you start using Concepts
and things it'll make your life lots
easier but there's some other Real
Simple Things something that has tripped
me up hundreds of times and I'll keep
doing is forgetting a semicolon
somewhere and years ago you'd get
thousands of compiler errors because it
would try and treat the next several
hundred lines as part of the same thing
and eventually you'll get internal
compiler error and everything would
crash around you now most of them will
say h did you forget a semicolon you
might get all the spew afterwards but
they are starting to spot some little
mistakes much more quickly so they're
much better than they were and respect
to the people who've spent a long time
trying to make things better for
hard work but better much better and
just to return to concepts for a second
what really surprised me you mentioned
does it support addition does the type
support is it a numeric type but what
really surprised me is you can say
something like the type must support the
function draw or resize or something so
you really can give it any function that
starts to sound like inheritance in a
way but it's happening at compos time is
that a choice you're going to make
whether to push it all into compile time
versus runtime absolutely I mean it's
being the case since templates were
there you could always do Dynamic
polymorphism with pointers and swap
things out that way and use Virtual
functions or you could do static
polymorphism they call it so the
polymorphism would be happening at
compile time and actually if you've got
a template that relies on something with
a draw method then you can vary things
out without having to build up a huge
class hierarchy and that's back to what
we were saying at the beginning about
different paradigms it's still
polymorphism but you're relying on
templates to swap things out or you can
have overloaded functions to swap things
out by type there's more than one way of
doing polymorphism and it isn't always
everything derives from object and it's
all virtual functions there's more than
one way to do this that leads into some
of my next question
which I think are doing things more
dynamically or kind of emulating what a
dynamic language would have so I'll just
mention standard variant and standard
any those feel like things you would
have in a more Dynamic language are they
done at compile time or is there a cost
to those
abstractions and there's optional as
well so those three tend to fall
together that gives you some options
haha to do things at runtime that would
have been much harder without these
different flavors of one of the
following or any old thing or possibly
maybe a value there is an overhead to
them but not much because C++ tries to
keep things as lean and neat as possible
I could come out with hundreds of
different examples where you would use
them but they're quite neat and they're
quite easy to use and they are useful
sometimes I've got an example in my book
where I start with a deck of cards just
practice building a class and it's got a
suit and a value and then we up our
Stakes a bit and we add some Jokers to
the pack now I could have built a big
class hierarchy and there a card and
it's either a card with a value or a
joker but it was much easier to go
variant it's either a card or it's a
joker and then I could pass a variant
with one of these two things around
everywhere and it's made it neater than
having a big class hierarchy and that
wasn't about dynamically swapping things
out it just made the code neater and it
was a chance to show how to use standard
variant you mentioned optional that kind
of leads to something I'm not sure it
was in the book which is exception so
right languages like I think rust and go
don't have exceptions and everything has
to be sort of an optional type in that
you return a value but you can check if
it's an error I'm wondering yeah when do
you recommend exceptions are used and do
you see them being used or do you see
optional as being an alternative to
exceptions well I mean the thing about
optional is you could check whether it
was okay or not and then what so I did
use optional to handle some user input
in my book and if the user didn't give a
number when you ask for a number well
maybe they want to give up so we'll stop
playing the game that works but that's
not exceptional like ah I've run out of
memory now what do I do now some
embedded systems don't enable exceptions
and you can compile up C++ code and not
use exceptions because some people
thinks it slows it down perhaps it
depends what you're targeting most
things on a PC or less environment
constrained will use exceptions but only
use exceptions for exceptional
situations right don't use them for
normal Paths of things and then optional
might be a better choice I didn't dig
into exceptions loads and they've been
subtle changes around exceptions and
loads of people have written loads about
them you can throw an exception you can
catch an exception but what are you
going to do with it if you catch it it
depends what's going wrong yeah they're
big topic loads of other people have
spoken at length about this they're
still there in C++ you can raise them
yourself you can catch them if you want
to but think about if you are going to
catch an exception think about why
you're catching it maybe it's better on
being passed up to the top perhaps have
a try catch block inside your main so
you can do something right at the top
level if something's gone horribly wrong
but there's still a thing yeah
exceptions are one of those features
that can be used very differently from
Project to Project based on the
standards of that project or can be a
jumble if this not stated how to use
them I mentioned variant and standard
any making it seem more like a dynamic
language in a way another one that I
really like like to see is called
structured binding and I really like it
because it reminds me of something I've
always liked in Python where yeah
structured binding is you can return a
pair or a I don't know what a vector
maybe and you can pluck out the
different values and assign them to
variables or a tuple or however one
pronounces the word tle Beyond pair
there are some circumstances where you
want to return two things from a
function and in instead of building a
struct and getting a struct at the other
end you can return a pair or a triple
three things in a tuple and then like
you said unpack them a compelling use
case there is if you're walking for a
lookup table so the maps we were talking
about earlier you've got a key and a
value and those used to be the first
part of the iterator and the second part
of the iterator that just L to hard to
read code but now you can say auto key
calledo value equals find a thing in the
map and then you straight away got them
insensibly named variables of the key
and the value so that's really neat yeah
I like that because then the collar can
choose to keep the tupple or keep the
the pair if they want yeah but they can
split it out if they want so it's kind
of the best of Let's see we did mention
the ranges library that is something
that feels a little abstract like I'm
not as clear it sounds like these are
algorithms and containers where you
don't pass begin and end but it seems
like it's more than just that yeah sure
so I mean traditionally if want to do
something with a vector and send it into
an algorithm I have to do my vector.
begin my vector. end which is tedious if
I use a range version instead I can just
send my Vector in like you said so what
like surely there's more to it than that
what we were trying to do with ranges I
think maybe partly inspired by link
in.net which allows you to filter or
take while or drop while or walk over a
collection of stuff maybe According to
some
criteria and importantly there that
supports lazy
evaluation right that's the deal so if
I'm filtering things or transforming
things it's not until I crystallize it
that I end up paying for things so it's
trying to make things more efficient I
think Andre
alexandrescu started talking about
ranges in C++ years and years and years
ago and he was experimenting with them
in D and that got everyone the C++
Community interested in thinking about
it and like I said inspired by lincoln.
net the idea of lazy evaluation if I
send a whole Vector into transform in
the standard Library I will get the
whole thing transformed after that call
where if I do the ranges version there's
a subset of ranges called views and
they're the lazy evaluation and it's not
until I actually start pulling things
back out of the view that anything
starts taking up Ram it's got some
clever skull duggery going on with the
iterators to make things work with the
lazy evaluation that's the Clincher yes
that's helpful that that's definitely
something I didn't pick up but I can see
how that's super useful especially if
you're iterating over a very expensive
container like that queries a remote
database or something I also saw ranges
I think lets you use the pipe operator
to chain together algorithms that's one
of those
C++ tricks I would say that sort of
blows your mind a little bit because
you're like how did it repurpose this
pipe operator can you say when you would
use that and maybe how did they do that
C++ you can overload all kinds of things
including the pipe op operator or the
comma operator oh who can come out of
all kinds of skull duggery just with
great power comes great responsibility
though so just because you can doesn't
mean you should but if you use Linux or
o based on that you're used to like
doing cat and then piping it to grep and
then piping it to something else so
you'll do the pipe operator between all
the things to chain them together and I
think that it does look neat and you in
atively understand that it is piping the
things together it's the pipe operator
and you can overload the pipe operator
so we did but that allows you to say
right here's my Vector I want to take
the top five and I want to filter by
whether it's odd or even I could do this
dot that dot the other but with the pipe
in between you can just have separately
on one line at a time what you're doing
and then it's kind of almost readable or
fluent you can see what you're doing
neatly but yes skull duggery of operator
overloading yes I think it's very
readable and another feature that comes
to mind that's related to sort of like
how did they do that are userdefined
literals I think it was in your book
where you talking about time and you're
actually allowed to have suffixes to
integers that are like Min Min n or Ms
millisecond or NS nanc that kind of blew
my mind I don't think I'd seen that
again how does that work what are they
overloading to allow for userdefined
suffixes I can't remember the details I
should know this it's basically is
function overloading again in terms of
what you read you can read and see oh 17
men that means 17 minutes you can
introduce your own literals too so if
you had colors going on you could talk
about RGB values for example or just use
your imagination there to see what you
can come out with it starts from the
idea of saying well if I want to say
I've got an integer and it's 42 I can
write in 40 xal 42 but if I want to
specify unsigned I put a u on the end
say it's unsigned or I can do a long
with an l or l l for long long and well
if I specify a string I've put hello
world in double quotes what I've
actually got there is a C style Char
array but if I want to put it into a
standard string okay but then it feels
like there might be overhead if I just
put an S on the end of the second quote
that then finds the function that gives
me string a standard string back rather
than the C style string so tiny little
feature and you can write your own if
you want one more small one and then
we'll go on to concurrency and
parallelism which I I wanted talk about
I think those are really relevant to
today but there's a C++ 20 spaceship
operator I looked it up and I think
other languages have it it's not unique
to C++ but tell us what the spaceship
operator is for it allows you to
add comparison operators to your own
type really quickly without doing any
work at all as long as you haven't got
something really complicated with
millions of fields in so if I've got a
struck well I back to the example of the
playing cards again early I've got a
struck that's got a suit and a value in
I might want to work out if this card's
better than that card so I kind of want
a greater than operator I could write
one by hand but I can use the spaceship
operator to not just if I've Ren a
greater than I then need a less than and
an equals as well if I put the space
spaceship operator in there and tell it
to just use the value will ignore the
suits then I've instantly got the
greater than the less than and the
equals as well for me it's a neat way of
being consistent if you don't do it you
can end up with incoherent greater than
less than an equivalence operators and
then you've broken all of mathematics
and got yourself a headache but it will
consistently generate things for you so
it makes your life easier and for people
wondering what it looks like it's it's
less than equals and then greater than
yes which looks exactly like a spaceship
right now I mentioned concurrency
imperalism these are huge features for
today's Hardware where you might have
100 cores and if you're using one out of
128 or something you're really leaving a
lot on the table so I guess two
different features one are co- routines
and one are exec ution policies and
maybe under the hood they use co-
routines or maybe threads I'm not sure
but can you talk about the push towards
more features for concurrency and
parallelism yeah it's a sure thing so
the execution policies we've mentioned
algorithms like transform and there are
plenty of other things there almost all
of them now have an overload that takes
an execution policy so you can say do
this in parallel there have some
circumstances where if there's some
sharing going on it can't tough but if
you got things that are clean and
immutable and it's taking a range and
list or vector of stuff and returning
some stuff so there's no shared state it
ought to be able to execute that in
parallel and yes it will be using
threads under the hood for you with very
little change you can speed things up
and get several things running in
parallel all at once just of that one
extra parameter in your function call Co
is a huge topic
there are other ways of doing parallel
things in C++ there's lots of threading
support there with Futures and promises
and async and all the rest of it and
Anthony Williams is the expert on that
go and read his book if you want to
learn more about this he goes in detail
there co-routines are kind of slightly
separate they they've been introduced in
C++
20 you need to do a lot of the work
yourself to make them work what it's
doing at a very high level is you write
a co- routine which is kind of a
function with some supporting structs
around it and that in effect gets
packaged up into stuff that can go on
the Heap so it can run for a bit and
then you can pause it so you would yield
the value you mentioned python just now
you can write a generator with the yield
C- word in and it a yield of value and
then when you call it the next time it
continues where it was the same happens
with a C++ co- routine essentially you
can yield a value from it and when it
hits that yield statement which is
spelled c coore yield in C++ of course
it yields the value back to the calling
code and because the state's packaged up
on the Heap next time you call it it
then teleports back into where it was
and continues so it works very like
yield in Python basically but it's all
packaged up on the Heap for you and that
allows a co-routine to call a different
co- routine when it's finished so you
can compose all kinds of bits together
and there's some really quite compelling
use cases I've seen Phil Nash talk about
loading up lots of data for well it was
yield curves it's an investment bank but
some of the input data needs more static
data to fit in bits so it wait until
it's got all the data it wants make the
next bit of the curve then return and do
the next parts you can piece together
lots of things being drawn from a
database and so on and because it will
just continue when it's ready you don't
need to decide who's going when or what
it just happens as it happens and it can
do things really quite efficiently once
something's ready the next thing will
then start so you don't need to thinkink
it through to me the real power of
co-routines in various languages is not
obvious at first but it's the fact that
you can decouple the amount of
concurrency from the number of threads
so right you might have a thread pool is
size of the number of cores or maybe
it's 2x the number of cores but co-
routines you could have thousands or
tens of thousands and it's really very
efficient that way and that you're not
overloading the exactly yes okay I think
we're going to have to leave out about a
third of the topics because we're kind
of running out of time but this
concurrency and parallelism talk reminds
me of my overall impression reading
about C++
in the last what's been added in the
last say 10 years is that there is a lot
of convergence between languages so you
can see a feature gets added to language
a and then a couple years later it gets
added to B and I think that's happening
more than a lot of people realize where
if you do switch from language to
language a lot of features just kind of
come with you I guess yeah yeah
definitely I mean you mentioned the
structured binding looking exactly the
same as you see in Python I think C++ is
learned from other languages and maybe
other languages have learned about
generics from C++ which yeah goes around
comes around so I wanted to real quickly
mention three tools you point out in the
book that I think would really help
people if they're wanting to learn more
about C++ and I'm going to read all
three of them here and then you can kind
of say what they're for so one is C++
reference C++ insights and compiler
Explorer and I'll put link to these in
the show notes cuz I'm not reading the
actual URLs but I think you mentioned
all three of these I went to all three
they seem really useful can you say when
you would use either one of those so if
you're trying to look something up you
can spend money on the C++ standard or
find a preview of it somewhere but it's
huge and you'll get lost CPP reference
gives you kind of an executive summary
of this to an extent it's kind of crowd
source so you can edit this if you see
mistakes and it is converging on correct
I think that's by far and wide the best
reference site if you want to look
something up it's got one or two missing
bits and it hasn't got the full legal Le
of the actual ISO standard which makes
it easier to read but they might be
missing a few details but that's the
best place to check something that'll
probably keep you straight that's good
C++ insights that's Andreas fertigs
Design This all if you put in some
Modern C++ code we talked about the
trading return type afterwards how do
you look up what does this weird symbol
mean you can't Google that very easily
if you put the code in C++ insights it
give you a suggestion of what might be
happening on your compiler under the
hood and what it will be equivalent to
so it will fill in all the gaps for the
stuff that's syntactic sugar that's
there to make your life easier and then
you'll have more of a sense of some of
the temporary un structures that might
be happening in the background it might
give you more of an understanding of
what the code's actually doing and how
it's
implemented and the final one Matt
godbolt has written his compiler
Explorer so loads of people refer to it
as godbolt rather than compiler Explorer
he's a lovely guy and he spent ages on
this you put in your code and you can
make it run and tell you what the output
is so what it'll also show you the
assembl it drops out so I gave you an
example earlier of using Conex with
something complicated looking and then
you see the assembler and you could do
this in godbolt and just see the number
right there in what's been compiled and
as you scroll over things it will
highlight the line of assembly you're
looking at and point you back to where
the C++ code came from and people use it
to argue about what's more efficient
sometimes if you want to see if
something compiles on a different
compiler he supports loads of different
versions of things so if you get a
compiler error you don't understand
locally it might be worth seeing what it
says on a different compiler and that
save you having to set one up so yeah
thanks to Andreas and Matt for those two
tools they're really useful and those
bring to mind something which is these
languages are getting bigger and more
complicated but tools are also getting
more impressive and more featureful I
guess to sum up kind of what we've
talked about if I were starting a
project today and considering C++ what
would you say the attributes of that
project I should consider what would
steer me towards using C++ or not kind
of given what we've talked about it's
fun to catch up and learn what you've
missed out on for the last few years so
just go for it there'll be some cases
where it's not the sensible thing to do
if you just want to write a website well
you could write it all in C++ and send
it for own script them and it generates
some types script for you and it work
but that's probably over the top but if
you're doing some number work or writing
some simple games or possibly you want a
supporting library in the background
because C++ is quite good at
interoperating other languages go for it
try it out write some tests whilst you
go lean on the compiler use the type
system knock yourself out have fun and
related to that if you're learning C++
in addition to your own book what other
tips do you have for someone so they can
get over that initial intimidation maybe
of the the size of the language just
start small put some numbers in a vector
take it from there listen to some
podcasts to help you out maybe find
someone to talk to a friend of mine's
recently set up a slack group and we've
just been meeting up once in a while on
the intellect and it's really useful be
able to just say ah what does this
compiler error mean or this code looks
ugly how could I make it better so we
mentioned that I edit at Q's overload
magazine they've got an email group
anyone can join reach out to people get
some input from someone else find a
friend who will encourage you and help
you out if you get stuck don't just talk
to yourself or scream at your compiler
find some friends chat to people about
it anywhere else online you can mention
either for the beginner or maybe someone
that actually wants to get involved in
the standards whether contributing to
them or just following along what's
going on I'll have to dig you out to
link to share on the show notes but ISO
cpp's got uh great overview of how to
get involved in the standards and even
if you just if something strange happens
in your compiler even so not as far as
the standards report bugs you can easily
find a list of outstanding bugs for
visual studio up vote ones if you find
things speak out don't suffer in silence
talk to each other there's loads of ways
you can get involved how about finding
more about the book or following you
online can you give any links to that I
I'll put them in the show notes so yeah
sharing the show notes I'm hanging out
on Master on and Twitter and Linkedin
quite a lot so I'll share the links with
you and the book is there a page for the
book or yeah so I'll share that with you
as well there's a page directly at
Manning and it's soon to be released on
Amazon it says in the next few weeks
great thanks so much for for joining me
today Francis thank you for having me
this has been Philip Winston for
software engineering radio thanks for
listening
cheers thanks for listening to SC radio
an educational program brought to you by
It software magazine for more about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website at se-
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our Slack Channel at seo.
slack.com you can also email us at team
e-r. this and all other episodes of SC
radio is licensed under Creative Commons
license
2.5 thanks for listening